<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Balogun Stephen Taiye</title>
    <link>/</link>
      <atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Balogun Stephen Taiye</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Balogun Stephen, 2020. Built with [blogdown](https://https://github.com/rstudio/blogdown)</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/avatar.jpg</url>
      <title>Balogun Stephen Taiye</title>
      <link>/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>My Journey into Quality Improvement and Patient Safety</title>
      <link>/post/journey-into-qi-and-ps/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/journey-into-qi-and-ps/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I grew up into a nuclear family of four children - two boys and two girls. We rarely fall sick, I attributed this to completing the national immunization schedule and to a functional health system that teaches preventive medicine. Only once could I remember any of my immediate family members being so sick as to need hospital admission. I believed the health system was safe, timely, and that death could be avoided on most occasions simply by presenting early in the hospital. I was completely naive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This thought followed me through my secondary school days. Life kept smiling on me, I was very fortunate. I had friends who shared similar thoughts and had similar experiences too. Believing in the safety culture of the healthcare system, I decided to study medicine too, become a doctor and continue saving lives. All my experiences so far did not prepare me for what was to come. There was a big gap between the healthcare system that I imagined, and the healthcare system that exists. I believed for example that a pregnant woman who register for ante-natal early, keeps her appointments, and deliver in a healthcare facility should have a healthy baby and mother, at least on almost all occasions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clinical postings started in my fourth year of Medical School. Then I began to catch a glimpse of what truly exists. I realised the system is way more complicated that I thought; way beyond my imaginations. From economic challenges, to delay of access, and to failure of healthcare services to save some of those who even scale through the initial huddles and would have thought of having a short stay in the hospital.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My brother and I entered medical school at the same time. We were in the same class throughout the 6-year training. My dad must have been a proud father, having two children who would become Medical Doctors at the same time. He would occasionally joke about us marrying another set of twins, both of who are either doctors or nurses. I am sure it was a moment he looked forward to. Dad was diabetic about the time we entered medical school, and hypertensive shortly thereafter too. I could imagine him thinking he should be fine with two children in studying medicine. He did fairly well for the first few years. During our fourth year in school, he developed blisters on the back of his left foot. Luckily enough, it was during my junior medical posting. I had had contacts on the hospital ward with people with similar history but did present to the hospital on time. Together with my brother, we were able to convince him to present to his out-patient clinic where a diagnosis of diabetic foot was made and he was admitted. While we were fearful of the diagnosis given some of our experiences, we were also relieved that he presented rather early (almost as soon as the blisters were noticed), and that he should recover in no time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet, days rolled into weeks with him on the hospital bed. Series of near events and never events occurred from both human errors and complete systems breakdown. Once he needed blood transfusion and had a transfusion reaction needing hydrocortisone. The hydrocortisone was given at a high dose for almost 5 days instead of the prescribed 24 hours. Infact, they just kept giving the hydrocortisone until he had severe water retention making him so puffy before it was discovered. By this time, he was already past 6 weeks on hospital admission and has become very anxious. Yet another time, he was made to fast till about 5:00pm (for a diabetic client) for a theatre procedure that should not take up to an hour, yet the procedure was cancelled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The big shock came at about 2 months into hospital admission. He had just recovered from his wound that became infected because of the delay with his skin graft. He had become weak he need support to sit up in bed. He needed to eat, the family member staying with him went to inform the nurses about this at their station. She was asked to support him to sit up on feed. perhaps because she could not support his weight or because she felt carrying his head up on the bed was enough, she fed him a liquid diet but ended up aspirating in the process. That was the beginning of the end. He died less than 5 days later due to sepsis as a result of the aspiration (pneumonia).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I could not stop seeing similar stories all around me. Human errors everywhere, collapsing and failing health systems. The loss of a person is always 100% mortality to the family involved. More especially when they feel the death could have been avoided. Like the Donabedian model, failure structure and processes can only lead to one type of outcome, bad ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How do you convince people that the healthcare system saves lives? How do you convince people to present early to the hospital and not seek alternative treatment when the people they know that presented early did not come back home? How do you convince the family not to give up on their family member who is admitted, especially for chronic ailment? The questions were endless. The more I asked, the more questions kept coming. Is this the best our health system can do? What happens when I become a consultant, is this the same system I will be working in? I knew that like most of my colleagues, I probably would be forced to find my way to a country where the systems work. But then I could not stop thinking of the fate of the poor masses, and the extended family members I have scattered in the country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While still asking these questions, I wrote and passed my entry (Primaries) exams for Surgery Residency. But I could not bring myself to start the programme. I could see brilliant Surgeons who are handicapped by the health system and I was scared of becoming one too. I wanted to help the system, not to become drowned by it along the way. It was during this period that a colleague introduced me to 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://isqua.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ISQua Fellowship&lt;/strong&gt; programme&lt;/a&gt;. During the programme, I also had the opportunity of taking courses too from the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://ihi.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Institute for Healthcare Improvement&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://rcsi.com/leadership/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Royal College of Surgeons in Ireland (RCSI) &lt;strong&gt;Institute of Leadership&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Finally, I felt the burning questions on my mind being answered. The Fellowship programme gave me the much-needed direction. And so, began my journey into quality healthcare and patient safety.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, I started in the hospital where I was working. I established a quality improvement team which I led to implement a couple of QI projects one of which one the Runners-up award of the first 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://linkedin.com/pulse/sawubona-reflecting-isquas-annual-meeting-cape-town-south-cornue/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;ISQua International QI Competition&lt;/a&gt;. Then I moved to the public health space to be able to support health facilities and communities across the country most especially and the globe at large.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./qi_competition.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;ISQua first QI competition&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since 2013, I have continued in this light. Though the journey has not been easy (didn&amp;rsquo;t expect that it would), but it has been worth every bit of it. I find joy and satisfaction in the lives we reach through supporting and strengthening healthcare systems to deliver safe and quality healthcare which has led to improving health outcomes (performance indicators) across these sites. This has continued to fuel my passion and drive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to all those who have supported and contributed to my quest for quality improvement and patient safety, specially to 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://isqua.org&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;ISQua&lt;/a&gt; for providing the learning platform and the ISQua community for the support, the Medical Director and President of 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://olanrewajuhospital.com.ng/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Olanrewaju Hospital&lt;/a&gt;, Ilorin Kwara State where my practical QI experience started, and my mentors, 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/AnthonyStaines&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Prof. Anthony Staines&lt;/a&gt;, and 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/davidjvaughan&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Dr David Vaughan&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My vision is a country where healthcare workers recognize the role of quality improvement and patient safety and apply these daily in our quest to delivering on our promise, health - the state of complete physical, mental and social well-being and not merely the absence of disease or infirmity, everywhere, every time.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>R for Healthcare Data Science (R4HDS)</title>
      <link>/project/external-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/external-project/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reducing Postpartum Haemorrhage</title>
      <link>/project/internal-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/internal-project/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In every country and community worldwide, pregnancy and childbirth are momentous events representing a time of great joy in the lives of women and families, but also intense vulnerability. Worldwide, over 300 000 women die due to complications of pregnancy and childbirth with most of the deaths occurring in sub-Saharan Africa and India subcontinent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Postpartum haemorrhage (PPH) – unchecked uterine bleeding after childbirth -  accounts for majority of these deaths.  For every woman who dies of pregnancy-related causes, 20 to 30 others experience acute or chronic morbidity. Generally, blood loss at delivery is under estimated. Primary postpartum haemorrhage (PPPH) is the loss of 500 ml or more of blood within the first 24 hours after delivery of a baby. It accounts for over 80% of postpartum haemorrhage. Preventing PPH is an important step in reducing maternal deaths. PPH usually occurs unexpectedly but can be prevented and promptly managed by simple and cost-effective evidence-based prevention plans and intervention including active management of the third stage of labour (AMTSL).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite the rich evidence of the benefits of appropriate management of labour in reducing PPH, yet many women do not receive this management due to poor adherence to standards. This creates a chasm between potential benefits of current knowledge and what is obtainable in most health facilities. Factors causing poor adherence have been identified and include incorrect performance of AMTSL, challenges with maintaining cold chain requirements of the uterotonic drugs, inadequate human resources, lack of written protocol for the management of labour, and poor monitoring, analysis and dissemination of measures to guide continuous improvement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project was carried out in a private hospital in Nigeria was able to achieve over 50% reduction in the incidence of postpartum haemorrhage using quality improvement approach. In addition, there were reduction in the rates of perineal tear and episiotomy during the same period.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;./pph.JPG&#34; alt=&#34;results&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Website Designing: my little experience</title>
      <link>/post/my-website-development-experience/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/my-website-development-experience/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started my data science learning in the year 2016. Initially, I came into contact with Epi-Info through a senior colleague. Along the line, I stumbled on the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.coursera.org/specializations/jhu-data-science&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Data Science Specialization course on Coursera offered by the John Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health&lt;/a&gt;. Boom!! I fell in love completely. Coming from someone without prior computer programming or website designing experience (I came from practically zero), and a practicing medical professional, I had initial turbulence. But my perseverance got the better of me 😄.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My initial interest was in the computing power of R, but I steadily became interested in other aspects including using 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://rmarkdown.rstudio.com/lesson-11.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;R for slides presentation&lt;/a&gt;, interactive charts, etc. The desire to customise the appearances steadily led me into learning about CSS and HTML. That was the beginning of my website design journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So far, I have built three sites, all consisting of static web pages. While my first two sites were built in the over 2 years ago, professional and family life got the best of my free time over the past two years. I came back to R very much about this year and I have been trying to catch-up with the rapidly developing and every increasing knowledge of R which I usually find overwhelming and intriguing at the same time. Here I share my experience building the three sites, two with R packages and the third one from the scratch (writing the HTML codes).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;first-website---rhdshttpsr4hdsgithubio&#34;&gt;First Website - 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://r4hds.github.io/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;RHDS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Built in May 2017 with R using the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://rmarkdown.rstudio.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Rmarkdown&lt;/a&gt; package. Thanks to the detailed 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://rmarkdown.rstudio.com/articles.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;documentations&lt;/a&gt;, I was able to build the site in short time. I had to learn a little of HTML and CSS thanks to 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.w3schools.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;w3schools&lt;/a&gt; tutorials. 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt; provided the hosting platform and a repository for my files. Though it has not been maintained in a while (I intend to periodically update it from this year), I use the site to share my analysis of healthcare data of open source data repositories of WHO and other United Nation agencies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;second-website---teehwys-worldhttpbalogunstbyethost32comindexhtml&#34;&gt;Second Website - 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://balogunst.byethost32.com/index.html#&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Teehwy&amp;rsquo;s world&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following the success of my first website, and my initial knowledge of CSS and HTML, I became more curious about learning HTML and CSS. Thanks to the Coursera course offered by the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.coursera.org/specializations/web-design&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;University of Michigan&lt;/a&gt;. I began building my second website from the scratch writing the HTML and CSS codes myself using both 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://visualstudio.microsoft.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Visual Studio 2017&lt;/a&gt; and 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://code.visualstudio.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Visual Studio Code&lt;/a&gt;. Even though the site has only few web pages, I thoroughly enjoyed the experience of building a site from the scratch, and ensuring compliance with 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://validator.w3.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;validatorW3&lt;/a&gt;. While 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt; provides the repository, the site is currently hosted on 
&lt;a href=&#34;&#34;&gt;byethost&lt;/a&gt;. I will be moving it away from Byethost to either 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://netlify.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Netlify&lt;/a&gt; or 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Github&lt;/a&gt;in the next couple of months and will update this page accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;third-website---balogun-stephen-taiyehttpstaiyerbindio&#34;&gt;Third Website - 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://taiye.rbind.io/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Balogun Stephen Taiye&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Built in February 2020 using the R package 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://bookdown.org/yihui/blogdown&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;blogdown&lt;/a&gt; and Hugo.  There are pre-designed powerful themes that provide options from simple to complex that makes the experience a whole lost faster and easier. I am currently using the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sourcethemes.com/academic&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Academic theme&lt;/a&gt;, and I am literarily swept off my feet. The site is hosted on 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://netlify.com&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;netlify&lt;/a&gt; with github providing the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/stbalo2002/website2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;repository&lt;/a&gt; If you are ever interested in building a website using 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://bookdown.org/yihui/blogdown&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;blogdown&lt;/a&gt; and 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://gohugo.io/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt;, I think you will also find the links below very useful:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://alison.rbind.io/post/2017-06-12-up-and-running-with-blogdown/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Up &amp;amp; Running with blogdown&lt;/a&gt; by Alison Hill&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://amber.rbind.io/2016/12/19/website/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Making a Website Using Blogdown, Hugo, and GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt; by Amber Thomas&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think it is a good idea for every person interested in building websites to have a basic idea of how to build a site from the scratch. But for persons who are also interested in data science, the data science software can also be leveraged upon to develop powerful static websites that can be further customised for personal touch and appearance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I am not sure if I will venture into dynamic websites in the near future, I am definitely in love with the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://bookdown.org/yihui/blogdown/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;blogdown&lt;/a&gt; package for website building and I intend to continue to use it in the main time. Like 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://yihui.org/en/about/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Yihui&lt;/a&gt; said in his book &amp;quot;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>LICENSE: CC-BY-NA-SA</title>
      <link>/privacy/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>/privacy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My 
&lt;a href=&#34;/post/&#34;&gt;blog posts&lt;/a&gt; are released under a 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 4.0 International (CC BY-NC-SA 4.0)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
&lt;i class=&#34;fab fa-creative-commons fa-2x&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fab fa-creative-commons-by fa-2x&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;i class=&#34;fab fa-creative-commons-sa fa-2x&#34;&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Terms</title>
      <link>/terms/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>/terms/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Global Ministerial Summit on Patient Safety</title>
      <link>/talk/pss2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2020 13:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/pss2020/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Improving Isoniazid Preventive Therapy in HIV Clients - Lesssons from Kogi State, North-Central Nigeria</title>
      <link>/publication/conference-paper/tb-and-hiv/improving-isoniazid-preventive-therapy-in-hiv-clients/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/conference-paper/tb-and-hiv/improving-isoniazid-preventive-therapy-in-hiv-clients/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reducing Postpartum Haemorrhage in a Nigeria Hospital</title>
      <link>/publication/conference-paper/reducing-postpartum-haemorrhage/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/conference-paper/reducing-postpartum-haemorrhage/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Use of demand-driven approaches to improve the determination of TB burden amongst people living with HIV [PLHIV] across 28 health facilities in Nigeria</title>
      <link>/publication/conference-paper/tb-and-hiv/demand-driven-approach/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/conference-paper/tb-and-hiv/demand-driven-approach/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Handbook for national quality policy and strategy: a practical approach for developing policy and strategy to improve quality of care</title>
      <link>/publication/book/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/book/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
